We'll be right back.
But, no, if you're visiting with us this morning, find a Canvas Connect card.
You should have got it from that pretty lady up front and Sarah Flanagan, although she's pretty too.
But they will give you a Canvas Connect card.
Fill that out.
Drop it off at the Welcome Center.
If you're new here, we'd love to find out, maybe send you some sweet swag or something like that.
But our Wednesday night men's group is open.
They meet the second and fourth Wednesday of the month in the youth group.
They're watching the Chosen series.
I didn't see any of my people this morning.
Who's running that?
Do we know?
Oh, Ted's running it.
He put his hand up.
No, if you're in it now, you're done.
That's it.
But, no, you can find that on the app.
If you don't have the Canvas Community Church app, download that.
You can see all of our small groups and people meeting and stuff like that.
If you're not a man interested in the Wednesday night men's group, find other small groups that you may be interested in, and you can do that that way.
July 24th from 5.30 to 7.30 is our annual pool party that Michelle loves putting on.
If you haven't been to one of those, it's a blast.
Potluck style, bring like a side and hang out, and we'll do water slides.
And last year we did baptisms.
Maybe we do some baptisms this year.
I don't know.
But come and hang out with us for the pool party on the 24th of July, 5.30 to 7.30.
And that's all the announcements I got.
Is Mike Gad in here?
He's over here.
He's ready.
I knew he would be.
Thanks, Corey.
Good morning, folks.
We got back from Blazing Hope on – that was yesterday.
Thank you for your prayers.
This was probably our most challenging week.
We saw some great things happen.
We had a good group.
As always, we had the right group.
Our big projects this year were putting in a boardwalk around the resident homes to cover up.
They've got a natural spring that just keeps their paths really muddy.
So we put a raised walkway that we decided to light as well.
And it turned out amazing.
The residents love it.
The staff love it.
It was probably a $15,000 project that we did for $3,000.
And, of course, that $3,000 is budgeted because you guys are great givers.
And it is so much fun to do projects that we have a budget for that bless others.
So thank you for making that possible.
We also enlarged one of their riding pens.
So we got to dig holes.
And that's always a fan favorite for our crew.
The weather was actually not bad.
We've had worse weeks.
We've had better.
But it didn't rain.
It stayed.
The humidity stayed somewhat down.
And our worst issues for the week was sunburn and a couple of bee stings and a little bit of poison ivy.
I'll put a plug in.
If you have any poison ivy issues, go to West Oak Market and buy some jewelweed soap.
That stuff does amazing.
We had a good crew.
And the things that we had to overcome, God provided.
And so we were really grateful for that.
And God did some things and some lives.
And you'll hear stories from the folks on the team.
Appreciate the late-inning relief from Andy Moore and his boys.
They showed up Wednesday night and helped us get through the last couple of tough days.
Heyday was mainly the tough day.
And then digging more post holes and mixing concrete.
So thank you, guys.
Anyway, we're going to go again next July.
Let me know if you're interested.
I've already heard from several of you.
But thank you for your prayers.
Thank you for your donations.
And thank you just for your support for the ranch.
They definitely appreciate it.
Thanks.
Thanks to Mike and the whole team.
And, again, your generosity makes all of that possible.
If you don't know a lot about Blazing Hope, you can talk to Mike.
We've got information on the website.
It's a great ministry that impacts women who have experienced sex trafficking.
So super grateful for all of that.
I just wanted to, as we go into worship, I was not planning on him being here, but he decided he wanted to come.
So welcome to the stage, my beautiful baby boy.
Obviously, yesterday was a wild and devastating evening for our nation.
And so I just wanted to not ignore that as we go into worship.
And as I've been thinking about what to say, what not to say, all of those things, I just keep coming back to the words of Christ in Matthew chapter 5.
But I say, love your enemies, pray for those who persecute you, and that way you will be acting as true children of your Father in heaven.
For he gives sunlight to both the evil and the good.
He sends rain on the just and the unjust alike.
And we live in a culture that is highly emotionally driven.
And I think we are persuaded to hate one another based on different political opinions or ideologies.
We're persuaded to hate our enemies when people act out against each other in violence.
And I think it's the way of Jesus that we actually lay down our hatred and pursue love.
And the best way I know to stir our hearts towards love for people that we struggle to love is prayer.
And so as we head into worship, I just wanted to spend just a minute or two praying for everyone.
Praying for our nation.
Praying for all of you.
All of the emotions that you might carry into this day.
Praying for just anyone involved in the political scene right now.
May emotions de-escalate.
And may we as the church lead by example in loving our enemies as ourselves.
Father, we know that you are sovereign and that you are over all things.
And God, we just, we come to you in a really difficult time.
Acknowledging pain and hurt and emotion on so many different fronts.
Fear.
And God, we just thank you for Jesus who is the perfect example of how to speak grace and truth.
And he is the perfect example of loving your enemies as yourself.
He laid down his life for us.
Not because we deserved it, but because it's in his character.
It's in his nature to love.
And so God, we just, we embrace that, that witness and that example for humanity.
And we, God, as the church, we ask that you would give us supernatural strength to lead with love.
To go into spaces that are tense and difficult and emotionally charged and lead with love.
Because you loved us when we didn't deserve it.
And so, God, we follow your example in that.
God, just be with our country over the next few months.
Again, may the church be an example to the world.
May we be salt on the earth, light a city on a hill.
God, may you just do what only you can do in the hearts of people who are hurting and struggling.
It's in Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
You are good, you are good, and there's nothing good in me.
You are good, you are good, you are good, and there's nothing good in me.
You are good, you are good, you are good, but my fear is crippling.
You are true, you are true, even in my wandering.
You are joy, you are joy, you're the reason that I sing.
You are life, you are life, a new death has lost its name.
And though I'm running to your arms, I'm running to your arms,
The riches of your love will always be enough.
Nothing compares to your embrace.
The light of the world forever reigns.
You are more, you are more, you are more, than my world will ever say.
You are Lord, you are Lord, all creation will proclaim.
That you are here, you are here, in your presence I'm made whole.
You are God, you are God, you are God, of all else I'm letting go.
And oh, I'm running to your arms, I'm running to your arms.
The riches of your love will always be enough.
Nothing compares to your embrace.
The light of the world forever reigns.
And I'm running to your arms, I'm running to your arms.
The riches of your love will always be enough.
The light of the world forever reigns.
My heart will sing, no other name, Jesus, Jesus.
And oh, I'm running to your arms, I'm running to your arms.
My heart will sing, no other name, Jesus.
The riches of your love will always be enough.
And oh, I'm running to your arms, I'm running to your arms.
The light of the world forever and oh, I'm running to your arms, I'm running to your arms.
The riches of your love will always be enough.
And oh, I'm running to your arms, I'm running to your arms.
And oh, I'm running to your arms, I'm running to your arms, I'm running to your arms.
My heart will sing, no other name, Jesus, Jesus.
Praise His name in this place today, church.
Amen.
Most of you know this, but the Bible calls us to praise the Lord with all of our heart
and our soul and our mind and our body.
And I'm often convicted by my lack of ability to praise God with a reckless abandon.
Not worrying about the other eyes on me in the room.
What I've done that week, the guilt that creeps in, but just to give my heart to the Lord,
to love, to pray, to dance, and to sing.
And this next song, it's a new song, and I want us to learn the chorus right now.
And we'll sing the whole thing.
But it talks about how deeply we are loved by the Lord and how we need to abandon ourselves to Him.
And I know it's tough.
And I always think of King David pretty much in his, you know, tank top and underwear,
dancing in front of the presence of the Lord in front of the Ark of the Covenant as he goes into town.
The subject's watching.
And of course, like most men are really good at, it upset his wife.
She was upset about it.
But he said, he was bold.
I give him that.
He was bold.
But he says, look, I will be even more recklessly, abandoningly worshiping the Lord.
Well, let's paraphrase.
But that's what he said.
I will do even more than what you see me do today.
You think I'm undignified now.
I will be even more undignified.
And I know that we don't have to be undignified.
It's not for everybody.
But let's just abandon ourselves to the Lord as we learn this new song.
We're going to sing the chorus a couple times.
If I can find the right key.
So you guys can learn it.
And then we'll start the song.
So pick it up as best you can.
And I'm completely, deeply, sold out sincerely again.
I'm completely, freely, hands to the ceiling in ever.
My one life endeavor to match your surrender, to mirror not my will but yours.
I'm completely, deeply, I don't care who sees me abandoned.
Oh, I surrender all.
Not too bad.
We can do that one, right?
Let's try it one more time.
I'm completely, deeply, sold out sincerely abandoned.
I'm completely, freely, hands to the ceiling in ever.
And my one life endeavor to match your surrender, to mirror not my will be yours.
I'm completely, deeply, don't care who sees me abandoned.
Oh, I surrender all.
And something isn't adding up.
This wild exchange you offer us.
I gave my worst.
You gave your blood.
Seems hard to believe.
You're telling me.
You're telling me you chose the cross.
You're telling me I'm worth that much.
If that's the measure of your love, how else would I sing?
But completely, deeply, sold out sincerely abandoned.
I'm completely, freely, hands to the ceiling in ever.
My one life endeavor to match your surrender, to mirror not my will be yours.
I'm completely, deeply, I don't care who sees me abandoned.
Oh, I surrender all.
And I just can't get over it.
What kind of self-control is this?
You had angels at your fingertips.
But on the cross you remain.
And I can repay that kind of love.
But I can praise with everything I've got.
Since death had all its power robbed.
And just like the grave.
I'm completely, deeply, sold out sincerely abandoned.
I'm completely, freely, hands to the ceiling in ever.
My one life endeavor to match your surrender, to mirror not my will be yours.
I'm completely, deeply, I don't care who sees me abandoned.
Oh, I surrender all, and I surrender all, and I surrender all.
The whole of my heart, the best of my soul.
Each phase of my life is breath in my lungs.
Consider it yours, Lord.
All the glory forever.
And the great that you've won.
The praise of the heavens.
The kingdoms that come.
Consider it yours, Lord.
All the glory forever.
And the great that you've won.
The praise of the heavens.
The kingdoms that come.
Consider it yours, Lord.
All the glory forever.
And the great that you've won.
The praise of the heavens.
The kingdoms that come.
Consider it yours, Lord.
All the glory forever.
And the great that you've won.
The praise of the heavens.
The kingdoms that come.
Consider it yours, Lord.
Consider it yours.
I'm completely, deeply, sold out, sincerely abandoned.
I'm completely, freely, hands to the ceiling in ever.
My one life endeavor to match your surrender.
To me or not, my will be yours.
I'm completely, deeply.
I don't care who sees me, baby.
Oh, I surrender all.
And I surrender all.
Oh, you'll never leave me, baby.
Oh, I surrender all.
You are the light of the world.
Like a city on a hilltop that cannot be hidden.
No one lights a lamp and then puts it under a basket.
You are the light of the world.
Like a city on a hilltop that cannot be hidden.
No one lights a lamp and then puts it under a basket.
Instead, a lamp is placed on a stand where it gives light to everyone in the house.
In the same way, let your good deeds shine out for all to see so that everyone will praise your heavenly Father.
This is the word of the Lord.
People come together.
Strange as neighbors, our blood is one.
Children of generations, of every nation, of kingdom God.
So don't let your heart be troubled.
Hold your head up high.
Don't fear the evil.
Fix your eyes on this one truth.
God is madly in love with you.
So take courage, hold on, be strong.
Remember where our hell comes from
Let's sing Jesus
Jesus, our redemption
And our salvation
Is in his blood
Jesus, the light of heaven
A friend forever
His kingdom come
So don't let your heart be troubled
Hold your head up high
Don't be enough in evil
Fix your eyes on this one truth
God is madly in love with you
Take courage, hold on
Be strong
Remember where our hell comes from
Oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh
Jesus, our redemption
And our salvation is in his blood
Jesus, the light of heaven
A friend forever
His kingdom come to the Lord, his kingdom come
Let the praise go up as the walls come down
All creation
Everything with breath repeat the sound
All these children
Clean and pure hearts
Good grace, good God
His name is Jesus
Let the praise go up as the world
All these children
Let the praise go up as the walls come down
All creation
All these children
Clean and pure hearts
Good grace, good God
His name is Jesus
And Jesus
Our redemption
And our salvation
Is in his blood
And Jesus
The light of heaven
A friend forever
His kingdom
Sing that one more time
Jesus
And our redemption
And our salvation
Is in his blood
Jesus
The light of heaven
A friend forever
His kingdom
Come
Dear Heavenly Father
We thank you so much today
To be able to gather in your house
And I just pray
That you're with us
For our hearts and minds
To hear the message
Be with Brian
As he gives the message
And with us
The coming weeks
In Jesus name
I pray
Amen
Thank you.
Oh, good morning, church.
Good to see you again.
Thanks so much for joining us this morning.
If we haven't had the privilege of meeting yet, my name is Ryan, and I have the privilege
of being one of the pastors here at Canvas Community Church, and we are just so glad
that you are able to join us.
If you are new, if this is your first time, you picked an interesting week to show up,
and you'll understand why in a little bit, but don't hold that against us just yet.
We are in week 10 of a series about the life and teachings of the Apostle Paul.
We finished his biography through the book of Acts, just sharing how he went from persecutor
of the church to a martyr for the church.
And now we're looking at some of his practical teachings to the church.
And then later, as we end, towards the end of summer, we're going to look at some of his
more theological contributions to the church.
In the last two weeks, I have had the privilege of preaching first on missional living.
We talked about Paul's teaching to the church on missional living, is that we're called to
lay down our privileges, our preferences, our desires to win an argument in order to win
people to the message of Jesus.
That people become more important than us being right or us having what we think we deserve.
That Jesus laid down his life for us, and so we also ought to lay down our lives for others.
And then we said, if we are successful at that, if we live well missionally, we will end up
reaching people from different backgrounds, and that will cause a unity problem.
Because unity is really easy when your neighbor looks like you.
When your neighbor was brought up with the same political views as you, the same budget structure
as you, the same all of that.
It's easy to love your neighbor as yourself when your neighbor looks like you.
But what about when those in the church are different from different backgrounds and different
thought processes?
How do we forge unity in the midst of diversity?
And we said, Paul talked a lot about not being judgmental or hateful over things that are opinions.
And there are a lot of things that are opinions in the church that we actually elevate above
the level of opinion, and we divide and get divisive and angry over.
And so last week, we talked about forming unity in the midst of that.
And this week is going to build off of last week.
This week, we're going to combine both topics of missional living and unified lives in the church.
We're going to talk about how Paul encourages the church, the believers, to address sin inside
the church.
How do we not judge one another based on opinions, but then when it comes to believers who are
in the church claiming to be submitted to the lordship of Jesus and yet living totally in
opposition to the commands of Jesus, how are we as brothers and sisters in the same family
called to address one another when those things happen?
Because the reality is we will not have an effective witness outside of our walls, nor will we have
any real meaningful unity inside our walls if we choose to actively ignore sin in our midst.
And so it's important that we talk about that.
If you missed last week, I would encourage you to listen to last week before, or listen to last
week this week because these two messages go well together.
And what tends to happen with human beings is we like to emphasize one over the other.
And I'm putting them practically together on purpose because both of them are extremely
important.
But sometimes we love unity, and for the sake of unity, we ignore sin.
And some of us are more in the black and white rules thing.
And so we actually love addressing people's sin, and we don't really care about unity.
But both are extremely important.
So I'm intentionally preaching these messages back to back.
They build off each other.
We are called not to judge one another over matters of opinion.
But as we'll see in our passage today, we are called to judge one another over blatant,
repetitive, and unrepentant sin.
If you're new, welcome.
It should be fun.
All right, let's pray, and then we'll hop in.
Heavenly Father, you are good.
You are worthy of all of our time and attention and energy.
You are worthy of total surrender.
And yet, God, we so often cling to our desires, our wants, our preferences.
We say we're submitted to you as Lord.
We sing songs about how we surrender all, and yet we don't.
And God, you lovingly pursue us in the midst of our rebellion, not because you're some kind
of cosmic killjoy, but because you actually created us, and you know what's good for us.
And as a loving Father, you call us back to repentance and to righteous living, because that
ultimately will lead us to abundant life, abundant life that lasts.
God, we want that for all of us in this room.
That's why we're here today, to remember that you are our good creator.
You created us in your image, and you want us to find the full and satisfied life that you made us for.
God, lead us in that path today as we talk about a hard subject.
It's in Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
If you want to follow along with me in your Bibles, I will be in 1 Corinthians chapter 5.
1 Corinthians chapter 5 is kind of towards the middle to back end of the New Testament,
and you can find it on your Bible apps as well.
I have been experiencing lots of new phases recently, as I am a new parent.
It feels like every other week there's like a new thing for me to learn or a process.
And my most recent phase now is Rory is a toddler.
The poor PK is just getting used in sermon illustrations left and right.
My newest phase is a phase about correcting behavior, right?
And some of the older people in the room are like, wait, millennials correct their children's behavior?
Yes, some millennials correct their children's behavior.
And we're kind of working this out together.
And I genuinely can say, genuinely, I take no delight in correcting my son.
But I do it because I love him.
And there are certain decisions that he makes that can be harmful to him or to those around him.
And so I lovingly choose to lay down my preferences in order to correct his behavior
so that he doesn't hurt himself or somebody else.
And the reality is most of us who are parents know that there are certain levels of behavior
where the level of correction has to escalate alongside the level of behavior, right?
Right now he's a toddler, so there's not much level of correction that can get too high
because there's only so much that he can get into.
But depending on the level of mistake or the level of decisions being made,
the level of consequence has to sometimes rise with it.
For example, some really great, amazing, godly friends at our church from Pennsylvania
who had to walk an extremely difficult path with their youngest daughter.
She made some decisions starting around the age of 13 that led her to abuse alcohol.
That progressed by the time she was 20 into full-blown heroin addiction.
And throughout this process, from 13 to 20, her parents lovingly corrected her
at the level at which the behavior necessitated.
Until they got to a point, the hardest probably decision that they could ever make in their lives,
where they had to say, you can no longer live in our home.
They did not take delight in that decision,
but they knew that that decision was enabling her and harming them.
They did it through tears of sorrow and prayers of lament
with the hopes that this drastic measure would ultimately lead to her healing and restoration.
Spoiler alert, it did.
She had a radical encounter with Jesus.
We were there when she got baptized, and she is now pregnant with her second child,
walking with the Lord, super thankful for that.
But I share that story.
Yeah, we can celebrate.
We can celebrate restoration.
I share that story because what we're going to look at here in Paul in 1 Corinthians chapter 5
is something similar in the family of God.
He says that as brothers and sisters in the church family make decisions that are contrary to the will of God,
that are disobedient to God's commands,
it's actually our job as a loving family to confront sin in the midst of the body of church.
And he's going to say that there's a point at which that the rebellion,
the decisions are so harmful both to the individual, to the church,
and also to the world around us looking inside, right?
We're supposed to be salt to the earth, the city on a hill.
The world is looking in and saying,
you guys are ignoring this sin.
You guys are supposed to be different.
And so there's a point at which where Paul says,
okay, for the good of the individual, for the good of the church,
for the good of the world,
we ask individuals to leave the church through tears of sorrow and prayers of lament
with the hope of restoration.
Welcome to church again.
And our passage today, it's one of the most referenced passage for something that the church has come to call church discipline.
Anybody grew up in church, heard of church discipline?
Raise your hand for me.
Can I just say, we're really bad at naming stuff as Christians.
That's just not a good name.
Like, I don't like that name.
I'd rather call it church restoration.
Because again, the whole point, the whole process is all about the restoration of the individual,
the restoration of the church.
We just, we're bad at naming stuff.
So the goal is always restoration.
There are actually, as I was studying, I was actually shocked
that there are actually more passages about this process in the New Testament
than I was even super familiar with.
It's talked about more often than you would think.
And the second most famous passage comes from the teaching of Jesus himself in Matthew chapter 18,
where he lays out very specific steps for how this process should go.
It's intended to be a long and slow process that starts with someone close to you that you trust coming to you privately and saying,
hey, I see this thing in your life that you're doing that seems to be contrary to the teachings of Jesus.
Can you help me understand why you're doing this?
And ideally, that's where the process ends, right?
Ideally, a good Christian says, yeah, you're right.
I am doing this thing and I shouldn't be doing this thing.
And thank you for bringing it to my attention.
Ideally, that's where it should end.
But if it doesn't, the steps that Jesus lays out essentially are him turning the volume up on the correction.
You bring two or three other trusted brothers and sisters who love this person with no delight in it
and say, hey, you're doing this thing.
It is clearly in opposition to the teachings of Jesus.
You are clearly living in disobedience and sin, and it is going to cause harm to you and harm to us as a family.
Please, repent and turn back to God, receive the grace and forgiveness of Jesus, walk in obedience.
And eventually, as that process goes on, if the individual continues to be unrepentant and say,
I can do whatever I want, leave me alone, that's where we have to take drastic measures,
not that we delight in, but with the hope of restoration.
And I share all of that before we even read the passage,
because where we're at in the passage in 1 Corinthians 5 is at the very end of this process.
And so some of Paul's language is going to sound very strong and even harsh,
but we need to understand in the context that so many conversations should have happened before this conversation, right?
This is the loudest the volume gets in the conversation.
And so as we read Paul's language, I just want to make sure that we have that in the background of our minds.
So I'm breaking down the passage into three sections.
My outline for this morning so you can follow along ultimately is that Paul says we should do this thing called church restoration.
We should do it for the good of the individual that is in rebellion, in sin.
We should do it for the good of the church, local body of believers,
and we should do it for the good of the world around us.
That's going to be my outline.
First, let's look at for the good of the individual, starting in verse 1.
Paul says,
I can hardly believe the report about the sexual immorality going on among you,
something that even pagans do not do.
I am told that a man in your church is living in sin with his stepmother.
You are so proud of yourselves, but you should be mourning in sorrow and shame.
You should have removed this man from your fellowship.
Even though I am not with you in person, I am with you in spirit.
And as though I were there, I have already passed judgment on this man in the name of the Lord Jesus.
You must call a meeting of the church.
I will be present with you in spirit.
And so there will be power of the Lord Jesus.
Then you must throw this man out and hand him over to Satan.
And listen, this is where it's important that we focus on the whole point,
so that his sinful nature will be destroyed and he himself will be saved on the day the Lord returns.
So Paul ultimately says this process that should have been happening,
it's interesting that his language is actually harsher on the church than it is on the individual.
Because the church had ignored their responsibility to call out this sin.
This man was living in sexual sin with his stepmother.
This is a sin that's actually illegal in the Roman Empire.
The consequence for a secular person doing this was to be banished to an island by themselves.
And some of you are like,
it doesn't sound like that bad of a punishment right about now.
I wouldn't mind being on an island by myself right now.
But this is such a heinous act that even the secular world wasn't doing it.
And the church has totally ignored this.
And so Paul is going pretty hard at the church and saying,
you're actually not fulfilling your responsibility to love this individual
and to hopefully protect him from the consequences of his action.
It's important that we define what sin is at the beginning of this.
It's a word that we don't like to talk about very much in the church.
Sin is anything that is contrary to the will of God for our lives.
And like I said in my prayer at the beginning,
God doesn't give us rules because he's a domineering cosmic killjoy.
All of God's rules are in place.
Because when we disobey them,
we will ultimately harm ourselves and others around us.
God gives us rules to increase our joy.
And the church should know that more than anybody else in the world.
We are the ones whom he has given us the spirit that cries out,
Abba, Father.
We understand that he is a loving father who created us on purpose for a reason.
And yet, instead of agreeing with the father's loving rule and reign,
the Corinthian church chose to turn a blind eye to the sin of the individual and their family.
And partly because they ignored it, it escalated.
Sin escalates in our lives, right?
No genuine follower of Jesus wakes up one day and says,
you know what I'm going to do?
I feel like having an affair with my stepmom.
Right?
Like, that doesn't happen immediately overnight.
This is a sin that grows, that increases.
However, when we take steps in a direction towards sin
and our loving brothers and sisters see us going down a path that's destructive and we ignore it,
partly on us to allow that pattern to continue to grow.
In this particular case, like I said, it got so out of hand,
not even non-Christians would have tolerated this kind of behavior.
Paul says, you've ignored your responsibility to lovingly correct your brother,
and it has spiraled totally out of control.
And I don't think the Corinthians are alone in this.
I think many of us, probably most of us, if I had to guess,
are also eager to ignore sin in the lives of those around us.
Why?
Why do we do this?
Why do we often choose to ignore these restoration conversations?
Why do we often choose to not dive into this relational aspect where we're trying to call our brother and sister to obedience?
If it really is, if we believe it, if we believe that sin causes damage to us and those around us,
and we say we love our brothers and sisters that are around us,
why do we refuse or ignore this opportunity to speak life into them,
to invite them to repentance and to right relationship with God?
A couple of guesses on my part.
The first, I think we're often tempted to overemphasize our freedom in Christ.
We say, yeah, they're sinning.
We all sin.
And Jesus forgives us, right?
His forgiveness, His grace is unending.
It's bounding.
And so, really, at the end of the day, is it that big of a deal?
We're all doing it.
We all mess up.
Why should I step in and say anything?
Paul says in Romans 6 that when he preaches the gospel, right,
he preaches the amazing, unending grace and forgiveness of Jesus,
the temptation for us is to say, well, I'll just keep on sinning.
So God's grace can keep on expanding and growing,
and people can see that God forgives me even though I am totally in rebellion to Him.
And Paul says, no, absolutely not.
If you live that way, you have missed the point entirely
because sin damages us and others.
So we should be willing to enter into difficult conversations
with our brothers and sisters when they are in sin.
The second, we overemphasize the importance of an individual believer
to the success of the church.
We say, yeah, they're sinning, but they're really good at leading worship.
They're a gifted preacher or teacher.
They're such a faithful volunteer.
They give so much money to the church.
If we confront them in their sin, they'll leave, and that will damage the church.
This is such an earthly perspective.
Jesus will build His church.
The gates of hell will not prevail against it,
and no individual in the body is so important that sin should be ignored in their lives.
And yet many stories have come out over the last 10 to 20 years in the American church
where we have refused to address sinful patterns and behaviors in our leaders
because we're afraid of the fallout.
We're afraid of what people will think when it comes out,
and so we hide it and we cover it up.
And the reality is God is a good God, and He will not let sin go unpunished.
It always comes out.
And when the world sees that we're refusing to address it and hide it and cover it up,
it actually leads to worse things.
The best time to address sin is before it gets out of hand.
The third thing I think we do is we overemphasize love of self.
So we often justify not approaching someone for a hard conversation about sin in their lives
because we say, well, I love them.
I love our friendship.
I don't want to get, I don't want to mess anything up.
I don't want to hurt them.
I don't want to hurt our relationship.
And this is love of self disguised as love of others.
We love our own comfort too much that we're unwilling to do something that makes us uncomfortable.
And Paul says that it's actually for the good of our brother and sister
that we should step into this really difficult thing for love of them.
But we justify, we say, no, I don't want to do that.
And actually, we're just loving ourselves more than we're loving our brother or sister.
The individual that we are claiming to love is the one who will suffer the consequences when it spirals out of control.
I've personally been in a situation before, multiple situations, but one that I remember fondly.
And I literally almost talked myself out of having a conversation that I knew that needed to happen.
Why?
Because I was putting my own comfort in front of the genuine love for my brother or sister.
I was saying, ah, this could be bad for our relationship.
This could be bad for our friendship.
This could hurt them.
And at the end of the day, it wasn't about them.
It was about me.
So I think we often ignore this in our lives because we're way more concerned with our comfort
than the flourishing of our brother and sister.
And Paul is angry at the church for ignoring their responsibility to lovingly confront sin.
Because at the end of the day, their brother is the one that is suffering the consequences.
And now that it has been left unaddressed, it has escalated.
And the only option is to remove him from the church.
Again, tears of mourning, prayers of lament with the hope that he will ultimately be restored.
Paul says, brothers and sisters in the church, it is our responsibility to confront sin lovingly
and in relationship with one another so that the individual can be restored.
It's all done for the good of the individual.
Second, he's going to say it's done for the good of the church.
Verse six, your boasting about this is terrible.
Don't you realize that this sin is like a little yeast that spreads through a whole batch of dough?
Get rid of the old yeast by removing the wicked person from among you.
Then you will be like a fresh batch of dough made without yeast, which is what you really are.
Christ, our Passover lamb, has been sacrificed for us.
So let us celebrate the festival, not with the old bread of wickedness and evil,
but with the new bread of sincerity and truth.
The second thing Paul says is we have to address sin in the church for the good of the church,
for the health of the church overall.
And he uses a masterful illustration that has both practical and spiritual implications.
And listen, it actually, it works both on an individual and a corporate level.
This is like master class preaching here in verses six through eight.
First, let's look at it on a practical level.
Just as base level as we can.
A small amount of yeast causes the entire batch of dough to rise.
Do we got any sourdough people in here?
Yeah, I love it.
So I'll take a, what are they called?
Feeders?
I need one of those.
Yeah, hit me up with that.
All right.
Right?
A little bit of yeast.
A very, very small amount of yeast spreads throughout the entire dough.
And Paul says this is how sin works, both in the life of the individual and the life of the church.
If you just allow a little bit, if you justify a little bit, if you theologize your sin away, if you explain it away, if you say, ah, well, it's not that big of a deal.
I've got it under control.
If we allow sin in our life unaddressed, it will spread.
Again, like I said, no well-intended follower of Jesus wakes up one morning and decides to go off the ledge of sin.
It starts much smaller and it escalates as we justify seemingly small amounts of inappropriate behavior that will grow and spread if left unchecked.
A few examples.
A little bit of gossip turns to slander, which gives way to bitterness and grows into full-out hatred that ruins relationships, causes damage inside and outside the church.
Man, I think this is not in my notes, but I think that's what we're seeing nationwide on a political scale, right?
We start with just a few jabs here and there.
And all of a sudden, it spirals out of control until there's full-blown hatred of one another, picking up stones and throwing it.
And we feel justified to do so because at stage one, we justified it.
At stage two, we justified it.
At stage three, we explained it away.
And now all of a sudden, we're standing with these self-righteous attitudes saying, I can do this because it's actually for good things.
You know what I mean?
So like it just, a little bit of sin grows.
A few envious thoughts leads to cutting corners at work, cheating, stealing, or a lack of generosity.
Social drinking turns into every night of the week and it escalates into a full-blown addiction.
A few lustful daydreams from a married individual gives way to regular pornography, which eventually gives way to a physical affair.
And on and on we can go.
We all know the stories.
A little bit of sin spreads like yeast throughout the dough.
You can't listen to me.
I need to listen to myself.
You cannot manage your sin.
You have to kill it by the power of the spirit of God that lives inside of you.
The same Jesus that rose from the dead has given you a spirit of power, not of fear.
But if we ignore it, if we choose not to bring it to the Lord, we try and manage it ourselves, it will spiral out of control.
Sin grows in the darkness.
So we expose it to the light.
And if we're not willing to expose it to the light, hopefully we have brothers and sisters around us who love us enough to say,
I'm going to shine a little bit of light on this sin in your life that you're hiding because it's ultimately going to lead to your destruction.
It's for the good of the church.
Paul would later write that we are called to take every thought captive and make it obedient to Jesus.
How often throughout the week are we filtering our thoughts through that idea?
Yeah, okay.
So then it also works on a corporate level, right?
Individual sin spreads in our life as we ignore it and justify it.
And sin also spreads throughout churches who are unwilling to address it.
When churches refuse to address open, obvious, and unrepentant sin in its members,
the rest of the members will get the message that sin is not that big of a deal.
Right?
Well, I'll just be like, ah, well, they're, you know, brother so-and-so is doing such and such,
and the church doesn't seem to be concerned with it, so my sin must not be that big of a deal.
And that is the worst thing that can happen to a church is if its members start to think that sin is not that big of a deal.
My prayer is that our church will be full of individuals who take sin seriously in their own life
and lovingly address sin in the lives of those who are in close proximity to them.
Now, I feel the need to say this at this point in the message so that we don't, with zealousness, apply it inappropriately.
The point of this message is not, I am not enlisting you as a private investigator of sin.
Right?
I am not asking you to start looking for every mistake that has been made by any individual in our church.
This is why we love small groups here.
This is why we encourage you to live in community, a small circle of brothers and sisters that you love and trust,
because you're much more likely to receive correction from somebody who sits around your dinner table,
who shares their own sin to you.
You're much more willing to receive that correction.
And so this process, it's meant to be done in community with people that you love and you trust,
and it's not meant to be every single possible mistake anybody ever makes.
Right?
We're all broken, fallen, sinners.
We make mistakes all the time.
We're talking about things that are left unchecked, things that have potential to spiral out of control.
He uses this illustration not just on a practical level, but on a spiritual level.
And for those of us that have some background in the Bible, this will flow pretty quickly into this,
but I'm going to do my best to explain it for those of you that are newer to the Bible,
or at least newer to the Old Testament.
If you're new to the Bible and you've kind of ignored the Old Testament for a while, I don't blame you.
It is really good.
You should work yourself into it.
But for now, he talks about this yeast illustration really is rooted in the Passover celebration.
And for those of you that don't know what Passover was, Israel was enslaved to Egypt for hundreds of years.
God appointed Moses to free the Jewish people.
He asked Pharaoh through Moses to let God's people go.
Pharaoh refused.
God sent multiple plagues throughout the entire nation trying to get Pharaoh's attention and say,
look, I'm going to free my people eventually, so just relent and allow this to happen.
And he continued to harden his heart and refused.
And finally, the tenth and final plague, God warned that the firstborn son of every family would be killed.
But if the Jews would obey God's law, sacrifice a firstborn spotless lamb and place its blood over the doorpost of their house,
God would pass over their house and not allow that plague to fall on them.
He would give them salvation from the plague.
Knowing that Pharaoh would relent and let the people go, he told them to get dressed and ready for a long travel.
And he told them to bake bread that didn't have yeast in it because they didn't have time for the bread to rise.
It's unleavened bread.
This happened just as God expected it to.
And from then on, every year, the Jews were invited by God to celebrate Passover by ridding their entire house of any yeast for a week.
The whole point of ridding their house of yeast was to remind them that God had delivered them from their slavery and death in Egypt.
And Paul says, this Passover feast, this ridding our home of yeast has so much more significant meaning.
Now look at verse 8, verse 7.
Now that Christ, our Passover lamb, has been sacrificed.
See, followers of Jesus, we believe that so many of the shadows of promises and covenants in the Old Testament are shadows of Jesus.
None more clearly than the Passover.
Jesus has replaced the sacrifice of Passover.
He is the great Passover lamb.
I love how John Mark Homer puts it.
He says, Jesus is the climax of the Passover tradition.
Jesus calls himself the lamb of God.
He was the firstborn.
He was without defect or sin.
He was crucified on the same day as Passover.
The timing gives the meaning.
This is the stuff that gives me confidence in the gospel message.
These things cannot be orchestrated.
These circumstances that Jesus was crucified, they could not have been orchestrated to line up perfectly with the Passover festival from thousands of years ago.
Jesus, he is our Passover lamb.
And now, listen to this, instead of ridding our homes of yeast for a week to remind ourselves of God delivering us from slavery in Egypt,
we are to daily rid our lives of sin, remembering that Jesus has set us free from slavery to sin and death.
We no longer have to walk in slavery to sin, but we can walk in freedom through Jesus.
We're called to take sin seriously in our lives for the good of ourselves, for the good of the individuals around us, and for the good of the church.
And it starts with you and me searching our own lives, daily inviting the Holy Spirit to convict, to challenge, to encourage us to repentance, and to walk in holiness.
Lastly, Paul's going to say that we do this for the good of the world.
Verse 9, when I wrote to you before, I told you not to associate with people who indulge in sexual sin.
So Paul's already written them a letter about this.
They've had a conversation about it.
And like churches often do, the Corinthians totally misunderstood and misapplied what Paul was saying.
He says, I wasn't talking about unbelievers who indulge in sexual sin, or who are greedy, or who cheat people, or who worship idols.
You'd have to leave the world to avoid people like that.
I meant that you are not to associate with anyone who claims to be a believer, and yet indulges in sexual sin, or is greedy, or worships idols, or is abusive, or is a drunkard, or cheats people.
Don't even eat with such people.
It isn't my responsibility to judge those who are outside the church, but it is certainly your responsibility to judge those inside the church who are sinning.
God will judge those outside the church, but the Scripture says you must remove the evil person from among you.
See, Paul had written, he'd heard whiffs of this issue before, and he'd written to them and said, you gotta address this.
And if they don't change, you can't associate with them.
And the Corinthians are like, okay, so don't hang out with sinners.
Got it.
Perfect.
Paul's like, no, that's not what I said.
There are people outside of the church that are going to do all kinds of sinful things, and that is, your job is not to distance yourself from them.
Your job is to love them with the message of Jesus.
We talked about this a few weeks ago, missional living.
But inside the church, that's where we are not to associate with people.
And instead, the church got it backwards, and how often has the American church fallen prey to this exact same thing?
How often are we so judgmental of those outside the church?
How often do we paint up our picket signs and show up to protest non-Christian people not living according to Christian standards?
Why would we ever expect them to do that?
And meanwhile, those same people with the picket signs, protesting, and casting judgment on people who don't know Jesus are ignoring sin inside the church of people who do know Jesus.
Isn't it crazy that the church 2,000 years ago did the same thing that we do today?
The condition of the human heart, we're fallen.
Paul says our job is not to cast judgment on people outside of the church.
We can't expect those who are not submitted to the lordship of Jesus to be obedient to his teachings.
That would be crazy.
Our job is to welcome them around the table in love, listen to their stories, ask questions about their experiences,
and look for opportunities to share with them the hope that we have found in Jesus.
But for the church, as we read from the words of Jesus earlier,
we, the church, are called to be salt to the earth, and what good is salt if it isn't salty anymore?
What good is our lives to the world around us if our lives don't look any different?
If we handle politics the same way the world handles politics,
if we handle judgment and anger and hypocrisy the same way,
what good is the message of Jesus setting people free from the bondage of slavery to sin if we live in slavery to sin?
We are like salt with no flavor.
We are like a light that hides ourselves under a bushel when we refuse to be in relationship with those who don't follow Jesus.
If you don't hear anything else for the entire time, here's my main point.
Write it down.
God has saved you to change you, and he has changed you to have an impact on the world around you.
God has saved you to change you, and he does that so you can have an impact on the world around you.
And many of us are content to be saved without changing.
Or we're saved, and we start to change, and yet we get to a point where we ignore our relationship with Jesus.
We're just proud because we're pretty good at this whole Christian thing,
and then all of a sudden we're separate out of relationship with God,
and we start to justify and theologize and explain away why we're in total rebellion to his commands.
When we choose to ignore our sin or sin in the church,
we are rendering ourselves ineffective to do the very thing Jesus saved us to do.
I'm by no means expecting perfection in the room.
Jesus himself knows that I am far, far, far from that.
But what he is expecting is intentionality and a willingness to address sin in our lives
and to address sin in our brothers and sisters who we have close relationship with.
Peter writes this,
But just as he who called you is holy, so be holy in all you do.
Jesus saved you to change you.
He changed you to have an impact on the world.
The reality is, I don't know about you,
but the people that I talk to who are leaving the church,
and I think the statistics in the American church would back this up,
they're not leaving faith because of intellectual doubts.
They're leaving faith because of the hypocrisy of the church.
They're leaving faith because the church is way too focused on sin outside of the walls of the church
and way too eager to ignore, justify, or theologize sin inside the church away.
What the world around us needs more than ever is a unified group of followers of Jesus
who take their own sin seriously
and who have radical compassion and grace for those outside the church in sin.
It's not that we ignore sin in their lives.
It's just that we don't expect them to change apart from having an encounter with the risen Jesus.
And this process of addressing sin in the church,
it's been my experience that it rarely escalates to the point where you have to ask somebody to leave.
Right?
This is not something that we're eager to do or excited about doing or that happens often.
But in rare cases, when someone who says they're submitted to the Lordship of Jesus refuses,
refuses to acknowledge the warning of their brothers and sisters who are saying,
you're headed down a road that's going to lead to your destruction.
The most loving thing that we can do is through tears of sorrow and prayers of lament
with the hope of restoration.
Not let them off the hook.
I've been a part of churches that take sin seriously for 10 plus years.
I've seen this get to this point maybe twice.
Maybe.
This is not something that we get excited about or want to see often,
but it's something that we have to talk about.
I love how Warren Wiersbe puts it.
He says,
the very act of church discipline,
let's call it restoration because we're bad at naming stuff.
The very act of church restoration is a testimony to the world
and a warning to the church,
especially to new believers that God expects his children to be different from the world.
To condone sin is to deny the very cross of Jesus.
Jesus died for the forgiveness of our sins.
And for us to ignore it like it doesn't matter or it's not a big deal
is to deny the very cross of Jesus.
So, as we begin to close,
this was not a particularly fun message for me to write.
Because me, like many in the American church,
we love to focus on the incredible grace and forgiveness of Jesus
while forgetting that he died to give us freedom from sin.
We have to take sin seriously because God takes sin seriously.
And God, listen to this,
God takes sin seriously because it's harmful to you and to those around you.
So, talking about sin is actually emphasizing God's incredible love for you.
He created you in his image.
He wants you to experience abundant life.
And you can't do that when you're in slavery and bondage to sin.
When you're trying to manage it all on your own.
When you're trying to hide it in the dark and hope that it goes away.
So, now what?
Do we begin a chain reaction of conversations
where all of us call each other out for every little mistake that we make?
No, we do not.
Here's what I would say.
Believers, if you're in here, you're a follower of Christ,
start with yourself.
Daily, allow the Holy Spirit to examine your life.
Give him the opportunity.
Give him enough silence in the morning to speak to you
and point out areas of your life
where maybe just a little yeast has crept in
and you've justified it or explained it away
or come up with a theological argument
for why it's not that big of a deal.
Allow the Holy Spirit to speak truth to your life.
Be willing to confess and repent
and move forward in obedience.
If you're going to have these conversations
with brothers and sisters,
do it in trusted relationships.
Root it in prayer.
Bathe it in prayer.
And if you're going to go,
make sure you've dealt with your own stuff first.
Do it in love.
Bathe it in prayer.
And only escalate it when it is blatant,
unrepentant,
and multiple conversations have happened
with multiple people who love this person.
This is why it's good for the church, right?
If our church is filled with individuals
who daily allow the Lord to examine them
and point out sin,
our church will become holier.
Individuals in our church will become holier.
These conversations will need to happen less and less
because the Holy Spirit is doing the work
and our hearts first.
And even when we have to have the conversations,
our hearts will be prepped and ready
because the Holy Spirit's probably already been convicting us
of the sin that our brother comes to confront us in.
If you're in here and you are not a follower of Jesus,
you're new to faith or the church,
this might seem weird or harsh.
The reality is Jesus has called his church to be obedient
so that our message is consistent and compelling.
He's called us to be obedient for the sake of the world
outside of our walls.
And we haven't always done that well.
We haven't always done that well
because we don't often like to have conversations like this
inside of our walls.
So you got to experience a family conversation.
And ultimately, I would tell you that Jesus
is the fulfillment of the Jewish Passover.
He died and rose again to set you free
from slavery to sin and to give you an abundant life.
He says that my way is easy and my burden is light.
If you're in here and you've never trusted in Christ
for salvation, you've never allowed him to bring you back
into right relationship with the Father.
I'd love to talk to you more.
We've got volunteers that are at this very beautiful looking prayer tent.
Actually, if you go inside, it's really nice.
I know it looks a little bit sketchy from the outside,
but we'd love to have conversations with you about faith in Jesus.
If you're in here and you have been made aware of an area of sin
that's gotten a little too far down the road,
that you've been trying to find a trusted brother or sister in Christ.
Someone that you trust and confess to them what's going on.
Ask them for support and help and encouragement
because you know the destruction that is at the end of the road.
We're going to pray and then we'll take communion.
Father, we thank you again for this opportunity.
Just so reminded this week, God,
of my tendency to avoid thinking about talking about sin too much
and just such a reminder that you're a loving Father
who gives us commands because you love us.
God, just the beauty of being able to, for the first time, correct my son.
Knowing that I'm doing it out of love and I want him to flourish
and have peaceful and beautiful relationships with us and with those around him.
God, in such a, so much of a bigger scale,
that is why you give us your teachings, your commands.
That's what the Sermon of the Mount is all about.
Your invitation for your children to live in accordance with your will
that will lead us to abundant life and freedom.
God, may we not shy away from addressing the sin in our lives.
May we have open, soft, receptive hearts
when brothers and sisters come and confront us.
God, may your church become more holy,
more effective at missions to the world around us
because we take sin seriously.
It's in Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
All right, we should have a map for you.
If you're new to Canvas, we take communion in an open way,
which means if you are a follower of Jesus,
if you have submitted your life to the Lordship of Jesus,
you're free to partake.
If you're not yet, if you haven't yet made that decision
or you're not sure if you've made that decision,
please just allow this time to be a time of prayerful meditation.
So, I'm going to dismiss.
We're going to follow the pattern on the map.
Get a wafer and a cup.
Come back to your seat.
And I will lead us in communion before we dismiss.
Go ahead.
Amen.
Once again in 1 Corinthians, if you ever want to feel good about yourself, read 1 Corinthians.
They're a bit of a mess, but so are we.
Amen.
Paul talks to the Corinthians about communion.
And yet again, they had kind of missed the point.
Again, often like us.
Though the wealthy were gorging themselves on the body and blood of Christ to the point
where they were getting drunk.
And by the time the working class got to the service, there was no bread or juice left.
And the followers of Jesus that were there were incoherent.
So there are worse, you know, there are worse things.
Maybe we're not doing as bad as we thought.
All right.
But as he gives them some corrective instructions on communion, he asked them to use the Lord's
table, the body and blood of Christ as a regular rhythm for them to examine their lives.
Are they living in accordance with what God has commanded them to do?
Are there areas in their life or areas in the communion service where they are blatantly disobeying the whole point?
He says this in 1 Corinthians 11, 28 and 29.
That is why you should examine yourself before eating the bread and drinking the cup.
For if you eat the bread or drink the cup without honoring the body of Christ, you are eating and drinking God's judgment upon yourself.
So communion, it is an excellent regular rhythm for us as individuals to do the thing we talked about today, to allow the Lord to examine our hearts, to make us aware of areas in our life where we're in rebellion, areas of yeast that we are allowing in our lives.
Why this bread has no yeast in it, to remind us that Christ's body was perfect, spotless, holy.
He invites us to obey him.
So, as we take communion, I'd invite us to take a moment to examine our lives, think about sin in our life, confess sin to God or to a trusted friend.
So, I'm going to give you another 60 to 90 seconds to just examine yourself.
And before you take communion, feel free to confess sin to God prior to taking communion.
If you feel like you want to let this time pass and go to a friend after church and confess, that is more than acceptable, no judgment.
Let's take just a moment of silence now.
Let's take a moment of silence.
On the night he was betrayed,
celebrating Passover with his disciples,
he did a radical thing.
He took the bread and broke it.
He said, this is my body.
This is no longer about a one-year-old spotless lamb,
slavery from, freedom from slavery in Egypt.
This thing is about me.
I am Yahweh in the flesh.
When you take this from now on,
you do it in remembrance of me,
of what I am about to do,
what I am about to accomplish.
And so we, together today,
take the body of Christ broken for us.
We drink the blood of Christ shed for us.
Jesus, we love you so much.
So, so thankful today for your forgiveness and your grace.
There's no sin too far,
no path too far walked,
that we cannot turn back and expect you to be running to us,
to embrace us with your grace and your forgiveness.
God, may we take seriously sin in our lives,
because we know that you love us and that you want the best for us.
And may we be a more effective witness to a watching world,
because we're being conformed into your image.
We love you.
It's in Jesus name I pray.
Amen.
All right, church, go in peace.
There are a lot of good sporting events on today.
So if that is anything of interest to you, enjoy it.
Thank you.